let's start off by talking about your
home what's your favorite thing about
your home my favorite thing about my
home would probably be my dog or my
sister I'm not sure because my dog could
be annoying sometimes in the morning he
likes to wake me up um but my sister is
almost the same person as me so I like
her company we like to do a lot of the
same things and we don't have that big
of an age Gap so we're similar in age so
we like to share the same Hobbies the
same music taste the same games and we
like a lot of the same things what makes
your home comfortable I don't want to
sound like I'm obsessed with my bed but
my bed I like being in bed it's super
soft um and also my rocking chair what
would you like to change about your home
I would like to have more windows in my
house because I like the sun and I don't
like being outside so much because it's
hot um but I like daylight so if I had
more windows in my house I feel like
that would make my house better now
let's talk about shopping where do you
prefer to shop I used to love shopping
at the mall but ever since this day and
age has been evolving I like shopping
online more do you prefer shopping alone
or with others I like doing a lot of
things with a lot of people and I've
tried shopping alone alone and I've
tried shopping with others I think that
I prefer shopping with others just
because I can get their opinion what was
your last important purchase I would
consider grocery shopping important so
food is that is that does that count as
an important purchase now let's talk
about your free time what do you like to
do in your free time I'm currently
obssessed with this new game on my
Nintendo so I like playing games how
often do you spend time with friends
I'm with friends almost every day I
wouldn't say that I make it a priority
but every day I spend time with my
friends be it going to the gym or even
just running errands together or just
going for a drive so I'll say every
other day what new hobbies would you
like to develop in the future I do want
to get into Pilates just more into
Wellness things because I I'm super into
like active stuff so like going to the
gym is what I'm doing right now but I
want to like expand that by going into
like Pilates or yoga stretching just
like a lot of like breath work things
like that now let's talk about food what
are the most popular foods in your
country adobo and Panet are my two
personal favorites and then for dessert
I like um Halo Hollow do you like trying
new foods yes one thing that I would say
about myself is I'm not afraid to try
anything from any country in comparison
to anybody else that I've met but there
are some foods that I wouldn't try are
there any foods that you really dislike
um so there's balut I don't know if you
would are aware of what it is but it's
like an egg but it's like a fetus of a
duck so that's that's something that I
don't like a skill that took me a long
time to learn um is singing and so the
reason why I wanted to learn how to sing
is because I wouldn't say it's like a
tradition where I'm from in the
Philippines but it's just like I grew up
just hearing people sing karaoke all the
time and I always thought like singing
is basically just the instrument of a
person and it was beautiful to me so
since I I was young I grew up just
watching people singing well listening
to people singing
and then once I got into
school um I think around the fourth or
fifth grade I started going into music
class where I would learn instruments
but it was like instruments can do so
much but I feel like the power of the
voice is stronger so I started to have
classes where I could learn to sing and
then also I would practice at home with
my family and we had our own karaoke
machine and my sisters were interested
in stuff like that too so we would sing
together or like we'd play I don't know
if you know the game band hero so we'd
play like like a guitar and drums and
then someone would be the singer which
would usually be me and another reason
why I was motivated to do that when I
got older when when I was in school we
used to have like talent shows I was
always like interested in music so I was
in the music side of school I guess and
um so when I was in music class I would
you know go to drumming contests but
that was boring then I started to go
into singing because everybody else
around me was singing and I wanted to be
that and then when I got to the talent
show I started doing better and better
and better and I won a couple times so
that motivated me but then um the
problem is that I've been
inconsistent like I would you know focus
on singing for a few months and then I
would stop and then I'd go back to it
and so I actually stopped for a few
years and then I only just recently
started trying to focus on it again so
we've been talking about a skill that
took you a long time to learn and we're
going to continue to talk about learning
and learning new skills what factors
determine how quickly someone can learn
a new
skill to thank you for watching this
video I want to give you a free course
that has helped thousands of students
improve their I speaking score what it's
going to do is take you through every
single part of the test and give you
strategies for part one part two and
part three and also allow you to
practice at home for free and get
feedback to sign up for that for free
all you have to do is just click the
link in the description thanks very much
and let's get back to the video so I
think well confidence and then like the
drive to want to do something like if
you're interested in it or not and then
also being consistent why do some people
give up when learning something
different ult um I think one of the
biggest factors would be comparison
let's say if you wanted to learn a sport
and you're with other people that are
good at the sport or for example when I
mentioned singing like everybody around
me was doing it and they were already
good at it and so if I'm participating
in competitions and other people are
doing better than me and I keep trying
and
trying it it makes me feel demotivated
because I compare myself to other people
what role does natural Talent play in
mastering a skill I think that's an
interesting one because because I'm half
Filipino people think that I'm just
naturally musically inclined where it's
like I was blessed with this talent but
I don't I don't know if I agree because
I don't know if it's because I'm half or
not but when
you're consistent and may be
easier and then it runs through your
family but consistency is what
what drives oh my God why was this hard
for
me I need to think of my answer I don't
know why
natural why does natural being blessed
with affect it cuz then I would be
discrediting
myself I just
say okay whatever I said just makes it
easier how important is having a good
teacher when learning something new I
learned that having a good teacher is
very important when you want to learn
something because personally in school I
struggled with math and I had tutor
lessons and then I would also just like
stay late after school with my teacher
but I never passed the class until I
took lessons with my best friend so
because we had a good relationship and
like I felt like she could understand me
um I think that it's super important why
does some old skills remain relevant
despite technological advances so
because technology is advancing by the
day everybody feels like okay the world
is just becoming technology focused
there are some talents that are
purely only where only humans can do
them so I think that you know they're
still important okay so let me give you
some feedback so I'm going to talk about
part one part two and part three give
you some general strategies and tactics
to to improve those areas and then we'll
talk about your individual marks your
band scores for the the individual
marking criteria so part one to thank
you for making it this far in the video
I want to give you 10% off our VIP
course I VIP course is the most
successful I course in the world that is
a fact because we have more band seven8
and N success stories than any other I
course in the entire world we do that by
simplifying the whole I process
supporting you with some of the best I
teachers in the world and being with you
every step of the way until you get the
score that you need all you have to do
is just look down in the description
just click that and you can sign up if
you have any questions about the VIP
course always feel free to get in touch
with us we answer 100% of the questions
that we get hope that you become a VIP
if not enjoy the rest of this free video
part one pretty good sometimes a little
short uh you could have expanded your
answers a little more I noticed that
when you're talking about your friends
or your family you're far more fluent
than when you're talking about more
abstract Concepts it seems as if you
find it very easy to talk about things
that you love so I would steer the
conversation towards those things most
of the questions are quite vague at
times such as your home your shopping
habits your free time when you involved
your dog or your sister sister or your
friends in those you were able to expand
your answers a lot more and you spoke a
lot more fluently now you weren't not
fluent all right you were very fluent
but it is a test and the examiner wants
you to expand your answers a little bit
more so they can judge your your fluency
and and your Grammar especially so I
don't think you will have any problems
with part one but if you can't talk
about someone you love or or something
you love um just try and steer it
towards something like an activity or an
object or or whatever that you're very
familiar with CU it seems that's your
comfort zone part two again I really
like the way you used a personal story I
would always recommend that you try and
do this that you don't try and make
something up or talk about something
just to that's more high level or
academic to impress The Examiner because
you are highly fluent when you're
talking about things that you enjoy real
stories from your life so always try and
use real examples and real stories I no
problem um with part two at all part
three you struggled a little bit more I
find that people who use real scenarios
and real life things when you you switch
gears and you ask them to think about
more abstract more academic things it's
not a criticism that they're not as
fluent it's not that you didn't answer
the questions but you could tell that
you just didn't know what to say at
times so what I would do for you in in
part three is again I would try and use
real examples these could be real
examples from your life or personal
stories about your real life so what
factors determine how quickly someone
can learn a new skill talk about you
know singing for example you can mention
that again or playing the drums or I
don't know what you're into but or maybe
it's something that you and your sister
were learning what role does natural
Talent play in MA mastering a skill I
really like the way that you used that
your um pod Filipino um and they're very
famous for for being musically inclined
you did lose track halfway through there
cuz I think you were again you were
going into talking more about culture
and genetics and all these different
things and whereas I think you could
just talk about do you have cousins in
the Philippines who are great at at or
you know on the other side of your
family are they not musically inclined
at all maybe you know but then I asked
you about a teacher and you immediately
started talking about your friend and
you were great I mean you know so this
is why I keep I know I'm repeating
myself everybody's different and for you
I think the best way to get one of the
highest marks is just to keep talking
about those people that that that you
care about let's now talk about your
individual marks so I think your biggest
strength H one of your biggest strengths
is your pronunciation you didn't grow up
in an English-speaking country but you
sounded like you sound better than a lot
of people who who who grew up in an
english- speaking country not just do I
understand you not just accent but your
your intonation and your sentence stress
is very very natural you convey a lot of
meaning through your intonation your
voice going up or your voice going down
when you're listing things you're doing
that and then you also use connected
speech sometimes very well um so I would
give you a bound nine for for your
pronunciation it is excellent there is
one area that I think you need to work
on we'll talk about that in a second but
let's talk about your other strengths
your vocabulary is excellent you use
idiomatic vocabulary very very well such
as this and you also use very high level
topic specific vocabulary such as this
you also use words very precisely and
very appropriately there's times where
you used simpler words and then there's
other times where you had to use more
advanced words like musically inclined
you could have said something like uh
Filipinos are good at music
but a more advanced way of saying that
is they are more musically inclined and
that is more specific topic specific
accurate term but the good thing is that
you you're not a try hard you're not
trying to use words like that in every
single sentence but because you don't
need to um you choose the right times to
use very high level vocabulary when it
helps you convey meaning grammar you
have no problem uh discussing ing any
any scenario and I didn't hear any
grammatical errors there might have been
a few little slips in there that I
missed um but no problem there so ban n
for grammar ban n for vocabulary 999 so
far so less than 1% of people in the
world who do the ISS test get a b nine
so it all comes down to the final part
you haven't got a b nine yet let's see
um let's see if we can help you with
that part which is fluency and coherence
fluency and coherence is is in one band
and you need to get both at a band nine
to get a band nine so coherence means
did you answer the question and fluency
means were you able to speak at a
natural pace without any hesitations
pauses audible pauses things like that
at times your fluency did stutter a
little bit especially in part three
where you were trying to think of
abstract ideas that is why I kept saying
over and over and over again just talk
about things that you care about when
you start thinking too much you uh and
then you stop and that will happen in
the real test because you will they will
throw very difficult questions at you in
part three because they think you're
good if they think that you are like at
a bond six or a b seven they won't ask
you many difficult questions in part
three but if they think this person
might be a bond eight Bond nine they
will through very difficult questions at
you to stretch your uh your ability you
also I don't know whether you're aware
of this most people aren't something
that people do a lot in Modern English
is they'll say filler words like like
you know like and you know there's
nothing wrong with that I try to stop no
no no no there's nothing wrong with that
the only time I would say you need to
improve that would be is if you want to
speak for a living like if you want to
be a podcaster or want to be a radio
presenter or a TV presenter or something
like that then you would really need to
work on it if it's just normal everyday
speech everyone else is doing it around
you so it's not a problem for the
purpose of the I test I don't think you
do it so much that it um affects your
speech everybody does throw in these
little fillers it's not a huge problem
but it does make you less fluent a
little bit at times I noticed that you
do it more when you're listing stuff and
then when you're trying to think of a
new idea you do heck you
know that way um not a problem but again
talk about things you're comfortable
talking about because when you do those
things are kind of are removed and then
we have coherence which is did you
answer the question and did you develop
your answer enough part one some of them
were a little short part three you got
you stopped halfway through sometimes
and had to think the examiner will base
your score not on one answer that was a
little short in part one or one answer
in part three that you had difficulty
with they will base it on the
entirety of your performance most
answers were were fine were no problem
at all but because some of them were you
wouldn't and because of the fluency
issues you wouldn't get the top score
for fluency you would get a band eight
but you are more than capable of getting
a bond nine so I think if you go and do
the test again you will 100% get a bond
nine